so before we discuss Branch fiction
let's have a reminder of what a branch
does in a pipeline a branch instruction
like this will compare registers R1 and
R2 and if they are equal jump to the
label this is usually implemented by
having in the immediate part of the
instruction field the difference between
the next instructions PC and the PC that
should be at the label so that the
branch effectively if R1 and R2 are
equal will just add the immediate opun
to its current PC so that the branch if
R1 and R2 are equal will add the
immediate operant to the PC that it
computed for the next instruction now
the problem with branches is that if the
branch condition is not met just
increment the PC for example if the size
of the branch instruction is four then
the PC will just move by four bytes
however if the branch condition is
satisfied in this case if R2 and R1 are
equal
then the branch will increment the PC
and also add the immediate to it so the
next instruction we fetch will be at
this label now let's look at what
happens when a branch goes through a
pipeline let's say we have our classical
Pipeline with a fetch read ALU memory
and right stages and let's say that
towards the end of the ALU stage we
actually figure out if a branch is taken
or not in the first cycle we fetch this
branch in the second cycle the branch
moves here where it reads the operant so
it's it's reading R1 and R2 but we have
no chance of telling whether the branch
will be taken or not so we either don't
fetch anything here or we fetch
something here let's say we fetch some
sort of a green instruction here at the
end of this cycle we still don't know
whether the branch will be taken we have
now read R1 and R2 but we haven't
compared them yet so when the branch is
in the Alo stage the green instruction
we have fetched after the branch moves
here and we fetch another instruction
let's say that's a purple instruction at
the end of this cycle we finally know
whether the branch is taken now there
are two possibilities either we have
fetched the correct instructions for
example the branch is not taken and we
have taken the instructions that follow
the branch the branch is not taken that
means the PC just gets incremented and
we fetch the right instructions in which
case we have no bubble in our pipeline
we can just proceed we fetch the right
instructions the second possibility is
that the branch for example is taken and
we f the next instructions in which case
we have to cancel these instructions in
the next cycle these two canceled
instructions move on through the
pipeline and we finally fetch the
instruction that we know is correctly
fetched so what happens is if we
correctly guessed what should be fetched
after the branch then there is no
penalty the branch finishes and then the
next instruction will finish right after
the branch however if we mispredicted
what will happen during the branch and
we fetch the wrong things then the
branch effectively took three Cycles to
execute because the branch actually
finishes in one cycle but then there are
two empty Cycles when we don't finish
anything so overall the cost of the
branch was really three Cycles instead
of one in our pipeline meaning the
branch cost us one cycle which is normal
for every instruction plus two cycles
because of a misprediction now you also
see why it never pays to not fetch
something after the branch if we don't
fetch anything after the branch until we
are sure what to fetch then we are
guaranteed to have two empty slots after
the branch so somehow in that case
regardless of whether we would have
guessed correctly or not we have a two
cycle penalty so we'd rather have the
two cycle penalty some of the time than
all of the time another thing that is
important to note is that at the end of
the fetch cycle where we fetch the
branch we don't really know anything
about this instruction yet we have just
obtained the instruction word meaning
the four bytes that represent an
instruction but we haven't even begun
decoding the branch so what happens is
next cycle we have to fetch something
based only on the knowledge of the
Branch's address we don't even know
whether it's a branch or not so when we
are fetching an instruction we don't
even know it is a branch but we already
have to make a prediction of whether
it's a taken branch